Did you know that guys need to have at least 3% body fat and women need to have at least 11% body fat for essential health?
I'm Carol Ann with Studio Group X and we're going to talk about how to calculate body fat.
Many people ask what is a healthy body fat range?
Well for men it is anywhere between 10 and 20% body fat and then for women anywhere between 15 and 25%.
Now what is that 25, 15% of what?
Well your body is made up of lean mass tissue and then your fat mass tissue so it's a ratio.
So for guys between 10 and 20% of your total body weight should be fat and then women 15 to 25%.
Now how do you measure body fat within your body?
Well there are several different ways that you can measure body fat.
The gold standard is what we call underwater hydrostatic weighing and basically you have a big tank of water and you have an individual sit on a scale and then totally submerge themselves under the water.
The second way that you can measure body fat is through infrared reading where you can measure the muscle tissue within the body.
Another way is called bod pod where you are measuring the body weight in air displacement and then another way that you can measure body fat is through skin fold calipers.
Now this seems to be pretty popular to get your body fat measured in the gyms or wellness centers or anywhere so basically what you do is you take this caliper and you measure different sites on the body.
You are measuring the thickness of the skin and you have what is called subcutaneous layer of fat underneath the skin and so you are just going to pinch different areas of the body and that's what we are looking at.
So a popular measurement is a three site measurement so you are going to measure tricep, abs, and thighs and then you sum up those skin folds, you put it into a formula and that is how you calculate your body fat.